Look Magazine Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Look Magazine Records 1934-1970 1948-1970
MSS86301
6,300 items
18 containers
7.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Biweekly, general interest popular magazine published in Des Moines, Iowa, from March 1937 to October 1971. Drafts, correspondence, notes and field notes, interoffice memos, reference materials, clippings, and other papers documenting Look's writing, editorial, and research processes.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Attwood, William, 1919-1989.; Berg, Roland H. (Roland Hobsbawn), 1908-1981.; Bowen, Catherine Drinker, 1897-1973.; Bruner, Louise Katherine, 1910-2004.; Bruner, Raymond A., 1900-1970.; Davidson, Bill, 1918-2001.; Kettering, Charles Franklin, 1876-1958.; Long, Margaret, 1911-1989.; Maas, Peter, 1929-2001.; Spence, Hartzell, 1908-2001.; Thompson, Dorothy, 1893-1961.
Subjects
American periodicals--Iowa--Des Moines.; Birth control.; Charities.; Cosmetics.; Crime.; Current events.; Epidemics.; Health insurance.; History.; International relations.; Pharmaceutical industry.; Poliomyelitis.; Politics, Practical.; Popular culture.; Rockets (Aeronautics); Sports.
Places
United States--Civilization.; United States--Culture.; United States--Foreign relations--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--20th century.; United States--Social life and customs--20th century.
Titles
Look.
Acquisition Information
The Look magazine records were given to the Library of Congress by Columbia University in 1995. They were transferred from the Prints and Photographs Division to the Manuscript Division in 2018.
Other Repositories
The Prints and Photographs Division of the Library of Congress holds the Look Magazine Photograph Collection (see http://www.loc.gov/pictures/collection/lmc/ ).
Access and Restrictions
The records of Look Magazine are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Administrative History
Look was a biweekly, general interest popular magazine published from March 1937 to October 1971 by Gardner Cowles, Jr., under various company names: Look, Inc. (1937-1945); Cowles Magazines (1946-1965); and Cowles Communications, Inc. (1965-1971). Look began as a tabloid-style magazine that emphasized sports, movie stars, and sensationalism. After World War II, it became more family oriented and included articles on social and political subjects, as well as regular features on personalities, food, fashion, and sports. Look's "golden years" (1954-1964) followed improvements in the magazine's design and focus by editor Fleur Cowles, art director Alan Hurlburt, managing editor Dan Mich, and others.
Courtesy of the Prints and Photographs Division, Library of Congress (http://www.loc.gov/pictures/collection/lmc/background.html)
Scope and Content Note
The Look Magazine records span the years 1934-1970, with the bulk of the material dating from 1948 to 1970. The collection documents Look’s writing, editorial, and research processes in this time period. The collection is organized into four series: Writer Files, Subject Files, Chronological Files, and Roland H. Berg Files.
This collection does not represent a comprehensive accounting of Look’s editorial practices. Each series only covers a portion of the magazine’s thirty-four year history with certain writers or editors more prominently featured in the materials, including William Attwood, Roland H. Berg, Bill Davidson, Peter Maas, and Hartzell Spence.
The Writer Files are primarily drafts of articles under consideration for publication in Look organized by the name of the writer. Published and unpublished articles by both staff and freelance writers, often with editorial notes, are included in the series. Some of the files also include correspondence and research documentation. Writers represented in this series include Catherine Drinker Bowen, Louise Katherine Bruner, Raymond A. Bruner, Charles Franklin Kettering, Margaret Long (Leonard), and Dorothy Thompson.
The Subject Files consist of research and editorial files related to a specific topic or article. This includes general topical research, research about individuals, letters to the editor, and field notes. Materials about the American zeitgeist feature prominently, as well as research about rocket technology in the post-World War II era.
The Chronological Files primarily consist of interoffice memos related to research, current events, and ideas for articles that are filed by month and year. They are to and from a variety of people at the magazine and cover a wide variety of topics including, but not limited to, cosmetics, crime, history, international affairs, politics, popular culture, and sports.
The Roland H. Berg Files document his role as the medical editor of Look and portions of his career as a medical writer and journalist. The writings section consists of materials written by Berg including articles for Look and other publications and correspondence and press regarding the books he wrote about the polio epidemic. The charity racket story material includes a typescript of the article by Peter Maas (“The Battle for Your Charity Dollar”), letters to the editor in criticism of the published article, and research materials, including Maas’ original notebooks. Berg was the editor assigned to the piece and was responsible for responding to the critical response it received. The general and topical files in the series include research files about the drug industry, health insurance and birth control, miscellaneous correspondence, and Berg’s membership certificates for The New York Academy of Sciences and The National Association of Science Writers.
Organization of the Papers
This collection is arranged in four series:
Writer Files, 1941-1962
Subject Files, 1939-1963
Chronological Files, 1960-1970
Roland H. Berg Files, 1934-1962
Container List
- Writer Files, 1941-1962 (Box 1-7)
  The Writer Files are primarily drafts of articles under consideration for publication in Look. Published and unpublished articles by both staff and freelance writers, often with editorial notes, are included in the series.
  Material types include drafts, correspondence, notes, interoffice memos, and clippings.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of writer.
  - Allison, Gordon, "Backers," undated (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Burnett, "Journey to Utopia, the Truth About Socialist Sweden," 1950 (Box 1)
  - Attwood, William, Eastern Europe story, undated (Box 1)
  - Auerbach, Aline B., "The Questions Parents Ask," 1954 (Box 1)
  - Bailey, Chuck, Story on Dwight D. Eisenhower's farm, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Balderston, John L. and Hewes Gordon W., "When an Atom Bomb Strikes...", 1949 (Box 1)
  - Barcella, Ernest, "A Day in the Life of President Kennedy's Personal Secretary," 1961 (Box 1)
  - Baxter, Batsell Barrett, "What is the Church of Christ?", 1955 (Box 1)
  - Benjamin, Burton and James Benjamin, "Last Trip of the Hindenburg," undated (Box 1)
  - Bowen, Catherine Drinker, "A Quarter Century, Its Human Triumph," circa 1961 (Box 1)
  - Bruner, Louise and Raymond A. Bruner, "Genius at Work," undated (Box 1)
  - Burke, W. J., "The American Scene," 1941-1948, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Burke, W. J., "The American Scene," 1941-1948, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Castan, Sam, "Mood of America, Milwaukee Industrial Worker," undated (Box 2)
  - Caumont, J. B., "My Trip in the USA," 1957 (Box 2)
  - Chew, Peter, "You're Under Arrest," undated (Box 2)
  - Christenberry, Robert with Tom Morgan, "Who's Kidding Who(m) About Boxing," 1954 (Box 2)
  - Cohane, Tim and I. R. McVay, "Verbatim Interview of Gene Melchiorre," undated (Box 2)
  - Cohn, Victor, articles on Russia and science, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Cook, Don, "England's Controversial Archbishop," 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Crosby, John, child welfare and adoption article research, undated (Box 2)
  - Daniels, Jonathan, "Southern Rebels, 1947 Style," circa 1948 (Box 3)
  - Davidson, Bill, "Fox Company," undated (Box 3)
  - Davidson, Bill, "Interview with Boris Morros," 1957 (Box 3)
  - Davidson, Bill, "Spencer Tracy," 1961 (Box 3)
  - Douglas, William O., various articles, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Duffy, Ben, "You Are What You Buy" and "Russia's Colonial Empire," undated (Box 3)
  - Eliot, George Fielding, "Ready-To-Fight Reserves," 1956 (Box 3)
  - Fischer, Louis, "Will Germany Go Nazi?", 1950 (Box 3)
  - Fischer, Louis, "The Red Man's Burden," undated (Box 3)
  - Frank, Jerome, "No Man is Safe," 1953 (Box 3)
  - Froman, Robert, "You Have to Think Like a Chicken," 1954 (Box 3)
  - Gallery, Dan, "The Rocket War," 1958 (Box 3)
  - Gardner, Mona, "Our Policy for Southeast Asia," undated (Box 3)
  - Gunther, John, "Inside England 1964" and "We're Winning the Cold War," 1963-1964 (Box 3)
  - Harrity, Richard, "A Foreign Legion of Faith on Greece's Holy Mount," undated (Box 3)
  - Heilbroner, Robert L., "Wanted, A Foreign Aid Program to Lead the Free World," undated (Box 3)
  - Jacobson, Dan, "Memo from South Africa," undated (Box 3)
  - Javits, Jacob, article about trip to Near, Middle, and Far-East regarding foreign policy, circa 1956 (Box 3)
  - Jones, Doug, Headshots, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Kennedy, John A., article on space race and Cold War, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Kettering, Charles F., "Let's Stop Buying Catastrophe," 1950 (Box 3)
  - La Cossitt, Henry, "The Paradise of Monkeys," 1953 (Box 4)
  - La Cossitt, Henry, "Canada Does it Better," circa 1955 (Box 4)
  - Leonard, George, "Is Fear Destroying Our Freedom," 1954 (Box 4)
  - Leonard, Margaret, "Freedom Ride," 1961 (Box 4)
  - Liedloff, Jean, Venezuela story, 1953-1954 (Box 4)
  - Marshack, Alexander, various articles, undated (Box 4)
  - Martin, John Bartlow, "The Strange One," undated (Box 4)
  - Maxwell, Arthur S., "Why I Know Christ is Coming," undated (Box 4)
  - Mayer, Martin, "Educating the Potential," undated (Box 4)
  - McCarthy, Joe, "Person to Person," undated (Box 4)
  - McGraw, James, "The Luckiest Girl in the World," 1957 (Box 4)
  - Melikov, Greg, "The Fight for College Press Freedom," 1956 (Box 4)
  - Menninger, Karl, "A Young Teacher's First Day in School," 1959 (Box 4)
  - Mitler, Ernest and Bill Slocum, baby trafficking story, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Newton, Virgil Miller, article on government secrecy, 1957, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Newton, Virgil Miller, article on government secrecy, 1957, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Northrup, Eric, "Should Doctors Go Back to School?", undated (Box 5)
  - Osborn, Robert, "Cirrhosis of the Psyche," 1956 (Box 5)
  - Perkerson, Medora Field, "The Mystery of Margaret Mitchell," 1955 (Box 5)
  - Phillips, Robert Becker, "New Orleans Mardi Gras" and miscellaneous material, undated (Box 5)
  - Poling, Daniel A., "My Father," 1956 (Box 5)
  - Porter, Amy, "Why Highway Accidents Start in Your Mind" (killed story), 1956 (Box 5)
  - Purdy, Ken W., "Edinburgh," undated (Box 5)
  - Pusey, Nathan Marsh, "The Greatest Challenge" (killed story), 1957-1960 (Box 5)
  - Raymond, Ellsworth, Vladimir Shabinsky article, 1957 (Box 5)
  - Regan, Louis J. with Andrew Hecht, "A Doctor Looks at Malpractice," 1955 (Box 5)
  - Reuther, Victor, "Let's Sell Democracy to Europe's Workers," 1953-1954 (Box 5)
  - Robbins, Jhan and June Robbins, "The Day the Slaves Were Freed," 1962 (Box 5)
  - Rogers, Edith Nourse, "It's Time to Guarantee GI Rights to Korean Veterans," 1951 (Box 5)
  - Roston, Leo, "John Hersey," 1950 (Box 5)
  - Rowlett, Margaret, "Now It's Our Turn," 1953 (Box 5)
  - Schorr, Daniel, American misconceptions of Russia, undated (Box 5)
  - Schorr, Jose, "Judge For Yourself, Real Life Dramas from the United States Courts," undated (Box 5)
  - Sheean, Vincent, "The Aftermath of Bandung," circa 1955 (Box 5)
  - Shirer, William L., "The Launching of World War II," undated (Box 5)
  - Small, Edith, "New Patterns for Living," 1956-1958 (Box 5)
  - Snook, Robert, "Why I'll Remain a General Practitioner," 1956 (Box 6)
  - Sparks, Fred, "What You Don’t Know About the War in Indo-China," undated (Box 6)
  - Sparks, Ned, "Royal Family of Severesque [sp?]," undated (Box 6)
  - Spence, Hartzell, "A Chosen People" (article on Mormons), 1957, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Spence, Hartzell, "America's Busiest Protestants," undated (Box 6)
  - Spence, Hartzell, "The Lutherans in America," 1957, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Spence, Hartzell, "Where are the Heroes of World War II," 1950 (Box 6)
  - Star, Jack, "Weather for Sale," undated (Box 6)
  - Stein, Herb and David Hanna, "The Toastmaster General," undated (Box 6)
  - Stevenson, Adlai E. and William Attwood, "Russia's Two Faces" notes, 1958, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Stevenson, Adlai E., various articles, circa 1956 (Box 6)
  - Thompson, Dorothy, "The Women's Manifesto," 1951 (Box 6)
  - Torre, Marie, "Did I Go to Jail for Nothing?", circa 1958 (Box 6)
  - Tichenor, George, "The Time I Robbed George Washington Bridge," undated (Box 6)
  - Twitty, Tom, "The Seven Year Marvel of TB," undated (Box 6)
  - Vandivert, William, "Changing Russia," 1960 (Box 7)
  - Van Dusen, Henry P., "What is a Protestant?", 1954 (Box 7)
  - Walker, Stanley, article on drought in Southwest United States, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Warner, Albert L., "The Other Fellow in the White House," 1951 (Box 7)
  - Woodbury, David O., "Our Future Lies in the Sun," 1955 (Box 7)
  - Wynn, Keenan, "Father is a Fool," undated (Box 7)
- Subject Files, 1939-1963 (Box 7-10)
  The Subject Files consist of research and editorial files related to a specific topic or article. This includes general topical research, research about individuals, letters to the editor, and field notes.
  Material types include correspondence, clippings, drafts, interoffice memos, and notes.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Art therapy, 1958 (Box 7)
  - Boom, amateur music, music in schools, 1956 (Box 7)
  - Cards, 1946-1962 (Box 7)
  - Clarke, Rodney, materials regarding alcoholic artist article, 1950 (Box 7)
  - Combat story, undated (Box 7)
  - Cuba, 1957, (4 folders) (Box 7)
  - Duse, Eleanora, 1950 (Box 7)
  - Gallup, George, 1939-1952 (Box 7)
  - Gannon, Billie-Marie, prize-winning school teacher, round-the-world trip, 1958-1959 (Box 7)
  - Gannon, Billie-Marie, Bill Davidson [?] notes, 1958-1959 (Box 7)
  - Gannon, Billie-Marie, travel journal, 1958 (Box 8)
  - Jews in America (letters to the editor, William Attwood), 1955-1957, (4 folders) (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous research topics: Joan Bunche file, 1958-1963 (Box 8)
  - Mood of America, morality in America, 1959 (Box 8)
  - Music in America, 1956 (Box 8)
  - New look in American living, 1954, (7 folders) (Box 9)
  - "Now Everyone Can Sunbathe," undated (Box 9)
  - Pearson, Lester B., 1949-1956 (Box 9)
  - Quiz bowl, 1959 (Box 9)
  - Recreation, 1955 (Box 9)
  - Rockets: Diplomatic, 1957 (Box 9)
  - Rockets: Grottrup, 1957 (Box 9)
  - Rockets: Map, 1957 (Box 9)
  - Rockets: Names, 1957 (Box 9)
  - Rockets: Occupation, 1957 (Box 9)
  - Rockets: Peenemunde, 1957 (Box 9)
  - Taste, pop, 1956 (Box 9)
  - Taste, serious, 1954-1956 (Box 10)
  - Vision and blindness, 1954 (Box 10)
  - Workers school, 1948 (Box 10)
  - World chronologies, 1954 (Box 10)
- Chronological Files, 1960-1970 (Box 10-15)
  The Chronological Files primarily consist of interoffice memos related to research, current events, and ideas for articles that are filed by month and year. They are to and from a variety of people at the magazine and cover a wide variety of topics.
  Material types include interoffice memos, correspondence, notes, and photocopies of reference sources.
  Arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - 1970 Nov.-Jan. (Box 10)
  - 1969 Nov.-Aug., (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1969 June-Jan., (5 folders) (Box 10)
  - 1969 Jan.-1968 Dec. (Box 10)
  - 1968 Dec.-Oct. (Box 10)
  - 1968 Nov.-Jan., (12 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1967 Dec.-Jan., (12 folders) (Box 11)
  - 1966 Dec.-Aug., (5 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1966 June-Jan., (6 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1965 Dec.-Mar., (10 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1965 Feb.-Jan., (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1964 Oct.-Sept., (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1964 July-Jan., (7 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1963 Dec.-Aug., (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1963 June-Jan., (6 folders) (Box 13)
  - 1962 Dec.-Jan., (12 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1961 Dec.-Aug., (5 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1961 June-Jan., (6 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1960 Nov.-Sept., (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - 1960 Aug.-Jan., (8 folders) (Box 15)
- Roland H. Berg Files, 1934-1962 (Box 15-18)
  The Roland H. Berg Files document his role as the medical editor of Look and portions of his career as a medical writer and journalist, including writings by Berg, material regarding stories he managed, and general research.
  Material types include correspondence, drafts, notes, clippings, notebooks, field notes, and certificates.
  Arranged in three sections: Writings, Charity racket story, and General and topical files. Sections are arranged alphabetically.
  - Writings (Box 15-16)
    - "A Report on Hospitals" article, research, correspondence, 1959 (Box 15)
    - "A Report on Hospitals" research [?], 1957 (Box 15)
    - "Are You a Sexual Athlete?", undated (Box 15)
    - "Bacterial Bombs: Can It Happen Here?", undated (Box 15)
    - "Clinic Crashers," undated (Box 15)
    - "Death In An Eye-Cup," undated (Box 15)
    - "Detecting Cancer in 30 Minutes," circa 1948 (Box 15)
    - "God's Medicine or Devil's Brew?", undated (Box 15)
    - "How Healthy are Health Drives?", 1959-1960 (Box 15)
    - "How Healthy are Health Drives?", 1960 (Box 15)
    - "How Healthy are Health Drives?" research materials, 1958-1961, (3 folders) (Box 15)
    - "The Not-So-Wonderful Wonder Drugs," 1946 (Box 15)
    - The Challenge of Polio, 1945-1948 (Box 15)
    - Polio and Its Problems, correspondence and press, 1947-1951 (Box 15)
    - "The Polio Story," circa 1955 (Box 15)
    - "Spurs to Medical Advances," 1950 (Box 16)
    - "There's a Window in Your Ear!", undated (Box 16)
    - "Wanted: A Medical Messiah," undated (Box 16)
    - "What Price Beauty?", undated (Box 16)
  - Charity racket story (Box 16-17)
    - "The Battle for Your Charity Dollar," Maas, Peter typescript, 1960 (Box 16)
    - Criticism, 1960, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - Research material (Box 16-17)
      - AID - United Givers information, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
      - John Price Jones Company, Inc., 1959 (Box 16)
      - Maas, Peter, notebooks for charity racket story, 1960, (3 folders) (Box 16)
      - Maas, Peter, research material, 1953-1960, (3 folders) (Box 17)
      - Material used for 1960 charity racket story, 1957-1960, (4 folders) (Box 17)
  - General and topical files (Box 17-18)
    - Birth control: Fertility/sterility story, 1957-1958 (Box 17)
    - Charity research, 1957-1960, (3 folders) (Box 17)
    - Charity research, 1957-1960, (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - Charities, social services research, 1960 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence: Maurice Goldsmith, 1954-1957 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence regarding Karl Menninger, 1958-1961 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1959-1961 (Box 18)
    - Drugs, 1953-1960, (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - Drug industry research, 1958-1960 (Box 18)
    - Health insurance correspondence, 1961 (Box 18)
    - Link Clinic, 1961-1962 (Box 18)
    - Membership certificates, 1934, 1954 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous research, 1956-1957 (Box 18)
    - Plastic surgery: "A New Nose Means a New Personality," 1960 (Box 18)
    - "The Rochester Plan for Cerebal Palsy" correspondence, 1951 (Box 18)